Guide to the Rice University Laboratory Equipment collection, ca. 1920s-2000s UA 384
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Laboratory Equipment collection
1920-2000
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 384
120 Linear Feet 120 items
This collection contains decommissioned laboratory equipment from a variety of academic departments on the Rice University campus.
Biographical / Historical
Over the years, the Woodson Research Center has saved decommissioned laboratory equipment from across campus.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains decommissioned laboratory equipment from a variety of academic departments on the Rice University campus. Each item has been numbered and is physically described.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Accruals
Additional materials are expected for this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Rice community.
Index Terms
Subjects
Laboratories--Study and teaching; Universities and colleges
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Laboratory Equipment
  - 88 MB Removable Hard Drive Reader (SQ5110), ca. 1991; annex_001; Brownish, biege, solid, plastic box with disk drive and metallic back
    General
    Manufactured by SyQuest; used to read removable hard drives
  - Removable Disk Storage (16MB), ca. 1984; annex_002; A large biege disk with central ridging
    Manufactured by Inmac; used to store removable disks
  - All-Service Gas Mask with Window Cator Canister Model 6, ca. 1960s; annex_003; A large, red trunk with black trimming, rusted metal corners, and an old leather handstrap
    Manufactured by Mine Safety Appliance Company; used to filter the air the wearer breathes
  - Unit Pulse Generator, pre-1960; annex_004; Medium-sized, black rectangular prism with 1 large, 2 medium, and 4 small knobs; a power switch; attached power cord; and 6 input spaces
    Manufactured by General Radio Company; helps create digital waves in a circuit (oscillates "on" and "off" states)
  - 7 Day Hygrothermograph, ca. 1974; annex_005; Gray, metal box with a glass top, venting on the right side, and a roll of paper with needle recording device inside; looks like a seismograph
    Manufactured by Weather Measure Corporation; measures humidity and temperature data over a week and records it on a chart
  - Oscilloscope Camera Model 196A with Special Wollensack Lens System, ca. 1962; annex_006; Small black box with strap, binocular eyepiece opening, two focusing knobs on the side, and large black metal protrusion
    Manufactured by Hewlett-Packard; used to take pictures of readings from an oscilloscope (device that measures voltage waves in a circuit)
  - Laboratory Standard DC and AC Ammeter, annex_007; Light-colored, wooden box with holes on the sides, an arched display, and 3 knobs
    Manufactured by Weston Eletrical Instrument Company; measures curent in both alternating current (AC) and direct current (DC) circuits
  - Assorted Carousel Slide Trays (6), ca. 2000; annex_008; 6 wide, short boxes of varying yellow, black, and red color
    Carousel Transvue 140 Slide Trays (4), Carousel Universal Slide Tray, Carousel Transvue 80; manufactured by Eastman Kodak company
  - Carousel 4600 Projector, ca. 2000; annex_009; Large, brown, cardboard box with big yellow and white label
    Manufactured by Eastman Kodak Company; used to project positive slides
  - Blue iMac G3 with Keyboard and Mouse, early 2000s; annex_010; Large clear and blue monitor with same color keyboard and mouse
    Manufactured by Apple Incorporated
  - Admittance Meter (2), pre-1960; annex_011; Heavy, metallic, circular devices of varying size on a mount with two very tiny holes on the side and a removable covering for chamber
    Manufactured by Philips North America and Electric; used to measure ease of current flow (similar to conductivity/resistance)
  - National Weather Service Radiosonde, ca. 1970s; annex_012; Ramshackle carboard and plastic box with conical protrusions
    Manufactured by Viz Manufacturing Company; used to measure atmospheric data on a balloon and then fall to the ground to be retrieved
  - SA1004 8 in 10 MB Hard Disk Drive, ca. 1981; annex_013; Black box missing cover with many openings and electronic components
    Manufactured by Shugart; used to read hard drive disks
  - Lubritact Rheostat Variable Resistor (2), ca. 1920s-1930s; annex_014; Large and long metallic tubes with coiling and a slidable black plastic piece with contact points on top of a wooden base
    Manufactured by James G. Biddle Company; used to control resistance in a circuit
  - Satellite T1900 Laptop, ca. 1994; annex_015; Small, thick, off-white, plastic laptop with printed screenshot of it in a Youtube video
    Manufactured by Toshiba
  - Graflex Optar 1000 Camera, ca. 1965-1973; annex_016; Large, black accordion of fabric with two attached plastic shutters mounted to a medium-long metal pole through adjustable knobs
    Manufactured by Rodenstock
  - Standard Cell for Low Temperature EMF (2), 1976; annex_017; Two baseball-sized, black boxes with large recatngular tower and two srewable black input covers
    Manufactured by The Eppley Laboratroy Company and Fisher Scientific; used as a standard for a voltage measurement at low temperatures
  - Wenner Potentiometer, ca. 1940s; annex_018; Huge, dark-colored, wooden box with three black knobs protruding
    Manufactured by The Leeds and Northrup Company; used to measure voltage
  - Unknown Optical/Electrical Instrument, ca. 1947; annex_019; Circular black base with metallic cylinder with glass window cutout protruding on three feet
    Manufactured by The Leeds and Northrup Company; purpose unknown
  - Millivolt Potentiometer, ca. 1930s; annex_020; Dark gray, medium-sized, metal box with dark leather handle, 4 loose wires, and multiple knobs
    Manufactured by The Leeds and Northrup Company; used to measure small voltages
  - Mode Locker Driver, 1978; annex_021; Gray box with black trim, metal handle, 3 knobs, 2 switches, and 2 indicator lights
    Manufacturer by Harris Electrical Instruments Division; used to synchronize waves in electronics
  - Actuator, ca. 1984; annex_022; Metal box with clear red-tinted covering and a loose braided wire
    Manufactured by Fujitsu and Centaur; used to convert electrical energy into mechnical motion
  - Plastic Scintillators with Attached Photomultipliers (2), ca. 1964-1972; annex_023; Triangularly prismatic wooden base with two protruding towers of foam, wood, wires, zip ties, and shiny foil
    Manufactured by Professor Robert C Haymes; used to measure radiation
  - Microwave Interlock System, 1983; annex_024; Small, gray and white, plastic box with protruding wire that attaches to a gray cylinder with white, circular tip
    Manufactured by Holaday Indsutries Inc.; used to measure microwaves
  - Vacuum Tube with Propeller, n.d.; annex_025; Glass bulb with thick propeller inside
    Manufacturer unknown; purpose unknown
  - Quartz Stone, n.d.; annex_026; A small gray rectangular stone with ridging
    Manufacturer unknown; used unknown, but likely electrical
  - Screwable Electronic Equipment with Two Leads, n.d.; annex_027; Small, gray, round metal piece with two tiny protruding copper-colored rods and a coiled cylinder
    Manufactured by Westinghouse Electric Company; purpose unknown
  - Radiotron Electron Tube, ca. 1950s; annex_028; Circular glass tube with protruding metallic rods
    Manufactured by Radio Corporation of America (RCA); used as a device to control current in electronics
  - Velocitron, ca. 1962; annex_029; Rings of varying gray, white, and biege color on a small cylindrical piece
    Manufactured by Polarad; used as a vacuum tube
  - Unknown Electronic Equipment, n.d.; annex_030; L-shaped, blue, metal cylinder with threading and a large protruding black plastic knob
    Manufactured by Oki Electronic Industry Japan; purpose unknown
  - Mounting Equipment, n.d.; annex_031; Small, metal, box-like piece with screw holes
    Manufacturer unknown; likely used to mount
  - Assorted Vacuum Tubes (7), n.d.; annex_032; Glass tubes with filaments
    Manufactured by GE, Sylvania, Hewlett-Packard, Raytheon, and unknown; used in computers
  - Microvolt Potentiometer and Electrochemical Cell, pre-1960s; annex_033; Large, wooden box with typed note
    Manufactured by Honeywell Denver Division; used to measure voltage and power a circuit
  - The Escort Overhead Projector, n.d.; annex_034; Dark, wooden box with black trim, a long black stripe going down the center, and venting
    Manufactured by Buhl; used to project transperencies
  - Genuine Whatman Filter Paper (9 boxes of varying size), n.d.; annex_035; Boxes of varying blue, white, and gray colors with circular blue and black labels
    Manufactured by W and R Balston Ltd.
  - Signal Generator Model 1001A, ca. 1950s; annex_036; Big, black box with many large knobs on top and and a circular indicator window as well as handles on sides
    Manufactured by General Radio Company; used as a power source for AC voltage
  - Geological Equipment with Spring and Lens, annex_037; Look across at shelfing behind you; it has a tripod, black base, central metal cylinder that is yellowish gray, secondary rusted cylinder with a platform and a lens attached to it, and a spring on top
  - Laboratory Scale, pre-1960; annex_038; Box shaped with a yellowing cover on it and a gray cord
    Manufactured by Sartorius
  - Dial Resistance Box (2), n.d.; annex_039; One small and one very large wooden box with many knobs surrounded by numbered metallic circles
    Manufactured by Leeds and Northrup Company; used to set the resistance in a circuit
  - Safety Centrifuge, post 1960s; annex_040; A large cone shaped metallic item with holes in its top and a rusted bottom cone
    Manufactured by Fisher Scientific; used in biology to seperate things based on density by rotating at high speeds
  - Planimeter, ca. 1969; annex_041; Inside small green felt box
    Manufactured by Gelman Instrument Company; used in drawing and measuring for scaling
  - Unidentified Metallic Bowl, n.d.; annex_042; Medium-sized bronze/copper colored bowl with ashes inside
    Manufacturer uknown; possibly for a laboratory purpose due to ashes in bottom
  - Unit Oscillator, ca. 1958; annex_043; Black device with a knob in front and a protruding cylinder in the back
    Manufactured by General Radio Company; oscillates voltage in digital waves
  - G2 Electrobalance Precision Scale, ca. 1960s; annex_044; Pale blue box with metallic insides and 5 knobs lining the bottom of the front
    Manufactured by Cahn; used to measure amounts accurately in a laboratory
  - Speedomax W Chemistry Recording Device, ca. 1960s; annex_045; Very large peeling metallic box with central window, paper inside, and a ruler on top
    Manufactured by Leeds and Northrup Company; records electrical or mechanical signal on roll of paper
  - Prism Spectroscope, ca. 1940s; annex_046; A metallic gray, water-tower-like device with a stem, tripod base, and large round top with three protruding tubes
    Manufactured by Gaertner Scientific Company; splits light from a source to identify individual wavelengths and colors
  - Voltmeter, ca 1900; annex_047; Wide and thin darkish wooden box with holes on side and black piece on top with arched viewing scale
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Company; used to measure volotage
  - Biology Scale, pre-1968; annex_048; Green, clear, and off white box shape with 4 knobs and a central cahmber with a hanging platform
    Manufactured by EH Sargent and Co
  - Desktop Microcomputer, ca. 1970s-1980s; annex_049; Thick keyboard with small screen
    Manufactured by Tandy Corp
  - An Optical Instrument (Refractometer?), n.d.; annex_050; Inside a wooden box with red velver cushioning and 9 written in roman numerals; actual device has a stage and long rod with lens
    Manufcatured by Spencer Buffalo USA; possibly used to measure refractive index
  - Digital Science DC50 Zoom Camera, ca. 1996; annex_051; Black and gray plastic box shaped device with small viewing hole and white and purple buttons
    Manufactured by Eastman Kodak
  - Unknown Cylindrical Piece of Equipment, annex_052; Large round cylinder with bronze coloration and black plastic protrusions as well as many random holes in it
  - Shark Model, n.d.; annex_053; Gray plaster model with inside of shark/organs shown
    Manufactured by Turtox Products
  - Assorted Laboratory Glassware (2 boxes), n.d.; annex_054; Inside large biege box labeled "glassware" (annex_054.1) and neighboring smaller steel gray box (annex_054.2)
    Various manufacturers
  - Plastic Petri Dishes (2 bags), n.d.; annex_055; 2 bags of watch-sized platic dishes with lids
    Manufactured by Falcon Plastic; used to grow cells in a laboratory
  - Fast Photodiode (3) with Extra Lens, n.d.; annex_056; Circular glass piece with rounded top, two red dots, and a colored, round glass piece on bottom
    Manufactured by ITT Electro-Optical Products Division; used for laser measurement
  - Micro Cover Glasses (2 boxes), n.d.; annex_057; Small biege box with glass rectangles inside
    Manufactured by VWR Scientific; used for covering specimens on a microscope slide
  - Microscope Lenses, n.d.; annex_058; Black plastic cylinder with glass centers
    Manufactured by American Optical; used to change magnification in a microscope
  - Slide Covers, n.d.; annex_059; Clear rectangles inside box
    WH Curtin and Co; used to cover specimens on microscope slides
  - Microscope Lens Equipment, n.d.; annex_060; Inside old blackish box; lens with attached gradated knob
    Manufactured by Bausch and Lomb; purpose unknown
  - 15x Eyepieces for Microscope (1 pair), n.d.; annex_061; Black cylinders with glass centers
    Manufactured by WH Curtin and Co; used as the lens you look through in a microscope
  - diSPo Soda Lime Glass Pipets (Pasteur Type), post 1953; annex_062; Cylinder with yellow, black, and white decoration filled with tapered glass tubes
    Manufactured by American Hospital Supply Corp; used to transfer and measure liquids
  - Telescope-Like Instrument, n.d.; annex_063; Square metal piece with long tubular protrusion in both directions and mixed pieces at the bottom
  - Electrical Energy Meter (kWh meter), n.d.; annex_064; Large black metallic box with large viewing window and many electrical pieces inside including needles, 4 oddly-shape things, and a paper for recording
    Manufactured by Westinghouse Electric Corp; used to record how much energy is used
  - Contactor from Rice Stadium, n.d.; annex_065; Green/blue/gray base with 4 rounded black ridges coming out of it and a mobile gray metal piece
    Manufacturer unknown; used as a switch for repeated changing of power to a device
  - Motor Starter from Rice Power Plant, n.d.; annex_066; Black box with holes on side with large circular pieces with arms protruding from it
    Manufacturer unknown
  - Vacuum Tube Multimeter, n.d.; annex_068; Gray box with black top and white lettering with lead wires coming out of it
    Manufactured by the Hickok Electrical Instrument Company; used to measure voltage, current, and resistance in a circuit
  - Thermometer Box, n.d.; annex_069; Inside large biege box; small wooden box with black top; very dusty; has 11 protruding metallic knobs and a black one as well as a square piece that detaches
    Manufactured by Leeds and Northrup Co; used to measure temperature
  - Unknown Object with Two Golden Spheres and Tapered Pointy Rods, annex_070; Medium-sized recatngular metal base with two metallic spheres of different size sandwich between two crossbeams on rods
  - Laboratory Scale Display, 1984; annex_071; Large circular metal piece with glass top and circular gradations
    Manufactured by Crosby; displays mass on a circular scale
  - Rocket Piece, n.d.; annex_072; 6.5' tall copper-colored cylinder with silvery tapered nosecone
  - AC Ammeter, pre-1960; annex_073; Handeheld black metallic box with glass viewing window
    Manufactured by Jewell Electrical Instrument Co; used to measure current in a circuit
  - Unknown Circular Electrical Recording Device, 1954; annex_074; Handheld black metallic box with circular viewing window and latched lid as well as needle inside
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; possibly used to record environmental conditions over a period of time
  - AC Voltmeter, pre-1960; annex_075; Black handheld box with arched viewing window and knobs protruding from side
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; used to measure voltage in an alternating current (AC) circuit
  - Condenser Substitution Box, ca. 1962-1967; annex_076; Rectangular prism with gray plastic front, a knob, and a red and a black input spot
    Manufactured by Heath Company; used to measure capacitance in a circuit
  - Milliammeter, 1942; annex_077; Black metal case with leather strap handle and a latch; very plain inside with a certification label, rectangular viewing window, and 2 knobs
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; used to measure small current values in a circuit
  - Decade Variable Resistor, n.d.; annex_078; Handheld reddish wooden box with black front and white lettering that includes two knobs with pointers and a red and a black input lead
    Manufactured by Cornell-Dublier Electronics Division; used to set the resistance value in a circuit
  - International Microcentrifuge, n.d.; annex_079; Metallic and curvy circular instrument with removable cover and holes inside to put tubes
    Manufacturer unknown; used to separate parts of a liquid solution by density
  - DC Ammeter, n.d.; annex_080; Medium-sized metallic black box with rectangular viewing window and 4 knobs with numbers below; labelled as B4A
    Manufactured by General Electric; used to measure current in a direct current (DC) circuit
  - AC Voltmeter, n.d.; annex_081; Medium-sized metallic black box with rectangular viewing window and 3 knobs with numbers and positive and negative signs below; labelled as C11C
    Manufactured by General Electric; used to measure voltage in an alternating current (AC) circuit
  - DC Voltmeter, n.d.; annex_082; Medium-sized metallic black box with rectangular viewing window and 3 knobs with numbers below; labelled as A12D
    Manufactured by General Electric; used to measure voltage in a direct current (DC) circuit
  - DC Milliameter, ca. 1960s; annex_083; Medium-sized black fabric container with strap
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; used to measure small currents in a direct current (DC) circuit
  - Precision Ammeter for DC and AC Voltage, annex_084; Square wooden box base with rounded top and holes in the side and a lighter-colored wooden top with same shape but smaller and arched viewing window; also present: two rectangular golden knobs and two rounded darker ones
    Manufactured by James G Biddle Company; used to measure current in both alternating current (AC) and direct current (DC) circuits
  - Educator Adding Machine, ca. 1912-1950; annex_085; Black mettallic base with black, white, and red buttons as well as a sliding triangular piece with numbers and various knobs
    Manufactured by Monroe; used to perform mathematical calculations
  - Precision Voltmeter, n.d.; annex_086; Wooden cubic base with circular glass window on top and two knobs
    Manufacturer unknown; used to measure voltage in electronic circuits
  - DC Voltmeter Model 45, 1945; annex_087; Opened wooden box with 4 knobs and an arched window
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; used to measure voltage in a direct current (DC) circuit
  - DC Ammeter Model 45, 1935; annex_088; Open wooden box with 2 metallic knobs and an arched viewing window surrounded by ridging
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; used to measure current in a direct current (DC) circuit
  - Electrical Testing Set No. 5300, n.d.; annex_089; Lightly-colored wooden box of medium size with broken leather strap and 5 large knobs inside as well as slihtly arched viewing window
    Manufactured by Leeds and Northrup
  - Single Phase Wattmeter, 1948; annex_090; Deeply-colored medium size wooden box with leather strap
    Manufactured by General Electric; used to measure power in constant current circuits
  - Wattmeter Model 310, 1935; annex_091; Dark reddish wooden colored medium sized box with leather strap
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Co; used to measure power in electrical circuits
  - AC DC Polyranger, 1958; annex_092; Medium large lightly colored wooden box with leather strap of same color and protruding black venting
    Manufactured by Sensitive Instrument Research Corp; used to measure current and voltage in circuits
  - Array of Vacuum Tubes with Propellers, n.d.; annex_093; Two metallic bases spanned by 5 metallic beams with white conical attachments and 8 vacuum tubes with red wires and clover-shaped propellers inside them
  - Decade Resistance Box, ca. 1953-1962; annex_094; Tall wooden box with black plastic front and 4 rectangular knobs and 3 circular input spots
    Manufactured by General Electric Co; used to measure and set resistance values in a circuit
  - Compensated Decade Resistor, ca. 1948-1956; annex_095; Tall wooden box with black front, 2 rectangular knobs, and 3 circular input spots
    Manufactured by General Radio Co; used to provide variable resistance in an AC circuit
  - Decade Resistance Box, ca. 1931; annex_096; Black plastic handheld box with very light gray front and 2 circular gray/black knobs and 2 black input spots
    Manufactured by General Radio Co; used as an adjustable resistor
  - AC Voltmeter, n.d.; annex_097; Open small black metal box with semicircular viewing window and 3 knobs
  - Phase Sequence Indicator, annex_098; Dark medium small wooden box with strap
    Manufactured by The States Co; used to indicate peaks and troughs in a wave
  - AC Voltmeter, ca. 1922; annex_099; Medium-sized wooden box with arched viewing and red nubs on the side as well as 2 knobs on top and one on front
  - DC Milliammeter, 1954; annex_100; Black metallic box with rectangular viewing window, strap, leather label, and two black knobs with protruding plastic pieces of either red or black
    Manufactured by General Electrical; used to measure small currents in direct current (DC) circuit
  - AC Wattmeter, n.d.; annex_101; Medium sized black metal box with rectangular viewing window, 4 black knobs above, and 2 black dials below
    Manufactured by General Electric; used to measure power in an alternating current (AC) circuit
  - AC Ammeter, n.d.; annex_102; Medium-sized wooden box with arched viewing window inset and 2 large black tipped knobs on top
    Manufactured by Weston Electrical Instrument Corp; used to measure current in an alternating current (AC) circuit
  - Rectifier Instrument, n.d.; annex_103; Black metallic piece with handle, circular display, and rectangular metal shell that can be adjusted by squeezing
    Manufactured by Ferranti Electric Incorporated; used to convert from alternating to direct current
  - DC Milliammeter, 1935; annex_104; Medium sized wooden box with hinged front and a leather strap as well as labelling on the side that says L7B
    Manufactured by General Electric; used to measure small currents in direct current (DC) circuits
  - U-H-F Admittance Meter, ca. 1964; annex_105; Pristine two-toned medium-sized wooden box with green label and a soft handle as well as a hinged top
    Manufactured by General Radio Co; used to measure the ease with which current will flow in a circuit
  - DC Ammeter, 1952; annex_106; Dirty medium-sized wooden box with two black nubs and hinges on front and a leather strap and latch on top